Finding Aid for Daniel Katz papers 1925-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings and Lectures
  - Articles written (arranged by date)
    - 1981
      - Organizational Psychology: Progress and Prospects (Box 8)
    - 1984
      - Ted Newcomb Obituary (Box 8)
      - Social Psychology in Organizations (Box 8)
    - 1985
      - The Development of Social Psychology as a Research Science (Box 8)
      - Social Psychology: Historical Overview (Box 8)
    - 1987 Helen Peak Obituary (Box 8)
    - 1988 Forward to Attitude, Structure and Function (Box 8)
    - 1992 The Development of Social Psychology at Michigan from the Perspective of a Participant Faculty Member (Box 8)
    - 1993
      - Rensis Likert and the Development of Social Psychology Beyond the Walls of the Laboratory (Box 8)
      - Social Psychology and ISR at Michigan: The Outcome of Two Strategies of Social Change (Box 8)
    - 1995, 1996 Untitled manuscript with Robert Kahn (Box 8)
    - 1996
      - The Development of Social Psychology as a Research Discipline and SPSSI's Role in that Development (Box 8)
      - Floyd Henry Allport: A Founder of Social Psychology as a Behavioral Science (Box 8)
      - Social Psychologists' Expertise in the Public Interest: Civilian Morale Research During World War II (Box 8)
    - 1997 The Story of Social Psychology: Its Ups and Downs (Box 8)
  - Articles written (undated; arranged alphabetically)
    - Abnormality and Insanity (Box 8)
    - The Beginnings of Social Psychology as a Research Discipline (Box 8)
    - A Comparison of the Radio and the Newspaper in Their Roles of Dispensing and Interpreting the News (Box 8)
    - Criteria for Organizational Functioning (Box 8)
    - The Decision-Making Process (Box 8)
    - A Developmental Story: Surveys and the Growth of Industrial-Organizational Psychology (Box 8)
    - Differential Criteria and Management Skills (Box 8)
    - An Electoral Contest in a Norwegian Province (Box 8)
    - Factors Determining Uniform Attitudes and Behavior (Box 8)
    - Industrialization in the Israeli Kibbutzim, Epilogue (Box 8)
    - The Kibbutzim as Open Social Systems (Box 8)
    - The Kibbutz as an Open System (Box 8)
    - Management and Ownership (Box 8)
    - The Meaning of Work (Box 8)
    - Organizations as Social Systems (with Robert Kahn) (Box 8)
    - Polls and Surveys as Methods for Analyzing Political Behavior (Box 8)
    - Power in Social Relationships (Box 8)
    - The Psychology of the Crowd (Box 8)
    - Social Psychological Factors in Interpersonal Relations Which Affect Involvement, Motivation and Commitment (Box 8)
    - Some Problems of Strategy in Cross-Cultural Research (Box 8)
    - SPSSI: Its Origins, Emergence, Its Impact and Growth, Its Maturity and Changing Role in Behavioral Science (Box 8)
  - Lectures (arranged alphabetically)
    - Group Process and Social Integration: A System Analysis of Two Movements of Social Protest 1966 (Kurt Lewin Memorial Award Address) (Box 8)
    - Introduction of 1973 Lewin Memorial Award Speaker, 1973 (Box 8)
    - The Meaning of Work undated (Box 8)
    - On Making Jobs More Satisfactory and Meaningful undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Ted Newcomb, Remarks 1985 (Box 8)
    - Social Change from the Perspective of Open System Theory 1974 (Floyd H. Allport Lecture) (Box 8)
    - Toward an Adequate Social Psychology 1950 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Published/Unpublished Materials 1969-1978
    - Revision of Social Psychology of Organizations (by Daniel Katz and Robert Kahn), June 1969-November, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Manuscript Index undated (Box 9)
    - Power in Social Relationships-Master Copy August 1974 (Box 9)
    - Survey Methodology: Its Development, Utilization and Potential October 1975 (Box 9)
    - Survey Methodology: Correspondence October 1976-January 1978 (Box 9)
    - Social Disaffection Among Deprived Groups (by Daniel Katz, Barbara Gutek, Eugenia Burton. Submitted to International Journal of Intergroup Relations), May-June 1976 (Box 9)
    - National Cleavages and International Integration: Norway and the E.E.C.-Chapter 2 draft (by Henry Valen and Daniel Katz) September 1974 (Box 9)
    - Norway and the Common Market-Chapter 3 (by Henry Valen and Daniel Katz) October-November 1974 (Box 9)
    - Norway and the Common Market-Correspondence (by Henry Valen and Daniel Katz) September 1973-February 1974 (Box 9)
- Topical Files
  Katz may have drawn upon his Topical Files (undated) for class lectures, as well. This collection contains a sample of Katz's extensive, though often illegible and scattered, topical notes. The contents in the first third of these folders were not appraised, reflecting the state of Katz's working files, while illegible materials were removed from the rest.
  - Frustration and Aggression (Box 9)
  - Group Conflict (Box 9)
  - Group Effects, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Groups, Nature and Types (Box 9)
  - Ideology, Ritual, Taboo (Box 9)
  - Industrial Conflict (Box 9)
  - Language (Box 9)
  - Laughter (Box 9)
  - Leadership (Box 9)
  - Morale (Box 9)
  - Morale and Motivation in Organizations (Box 9)
  - Motivation (Box 9)
  - Nationalism (Seminar) (Box 9)
  - Nationalism, The State (Box 9)
  - Need Achievement (Box 9)
  - Non-Conformity (Box 9)
  - Organic Nature of Culture (Box 9)
  - Perception (Box 9)
  - Personality (Box 9)
  - Public Opinion Attitudes (Box 9)
  - Theories of Feeling and Emotion (Box 9)